Guide to the Perry Brass papers, 1968-1992
Brass, Perry papers, 1968-1992
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Perry Brass papers, 1968-1992
7329
Perry Brass
4.4 cubic ft.
Diaries, scripts, erotica, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The Perry Brass papers consist of handwritten and typescript drafts of letters, articles, prose pieces, theatrical writings, diaries, poems, and essays, as well as photographs, publicity and promotional materials, scripts, letters to Brass from friends and family, and printed versions of articles as they appeared in various gay magazines. Most of the material in the collection is concerned with gay themes and the relationship between the gay and straight cultures; the correspondence also most often pertains to gay society, relations, or theatrical and literary milieus.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Perry Brass was born in Savannah, Georgia in 1947. He graduated from New York University in 1974, having studied art education. As a gay playwright, writer, and essayist, Brass' most successful work was the theater piece "All Men" which was produced in New York City, Los Angeles, and Chicago, in 1987 and 1988.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Manuscript versions of Brass' plays, stories, novels, and articles, mostly with gay male themes, including stage directions, programs, press releases and other promotional material for some of the plays, notably "All Men"; typescript of unpublished novel; original screenplay This is All of US, 1970; copies of COME OUT!, which Brass wrote for and published; professional and gay movement correspondence; course materials; and miscellaneous professional papers. Personal papers include a 1968 journal; student papers from NYU, 1971-1973; photographs; and personal and family correspondence.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Brass, Perry.; New York University--Students.
Subjects:
Come out!; Gay men--Drama.; Homosexuality and art.; Homosexuality, Male.; Pornography.; Gays' writings, American.; Erotica.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Scripts.; Erotica.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
PROVENANCE
The collection was received from Perry Brass in multiple installments in 1989 and 1992.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
As the collection arrived at the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections at Cornell, there was no evident or particular organization other than the one Brass provided to identify the components of his several donations. As with "All Men," which he called a "structuralist performance piece," Brass kept unlike forms together. These might include drafts of letters, ideas for essays, fragments of theatrical pieces, other forms of writing, and other material. These usually have a chronological integrity.
It is particularly useful to consider Brass' descriptive notes that accompanied each of the donations. These frequently became reminiscences or interpretations, and provide valuable insight into the works. These are located in Box 1, folder 58. Wherever possible, notation of the correspondence is made between Brass' original folder designations, and the current archival configurations. Other connections can be inferred.
The terms "holograph" and "manuscript" are for the purposes of this collection interchangeable.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal
Boxes 1, 3
Series II. Correspondence
Boxes 1, 2, 4, 5
Series III. Works
Boxes 1-5
Series IV. Miscellany, including photographs
Boxes 1-5
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal
  - Diary, 29 Apr. 1968 to 12 Nov. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brass vita; "12 Musical Figures for Christmas"; Young/Brass change of address note; "5 Gay Plays by Perry Brass" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diary, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Diary notebooks (Box 3, Folder 18-23)
  - Perry Brass' original descriptive notes of material, See also key to Brass' notes (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Letters to Perry Brass, from Rick Paul, Will Inman, Louise Landy, George Michell, Betty Deal, Christopher Hewitt, and others, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Letters from George Michell, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 17-22)
  - Professional letters and miscellany, mid 1970s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Gay Movement and Professional Letters, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Assorted Boyfriend and Personal Letters, 1970-1990 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Personal and Family Letters and Papers, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
  - Correspondence 1969-1971; Ian Young (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence Feb - Apr 1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence May 1980 - Feb 1982 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence 1992 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and typescript of "Men Keep House" 1987 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence Jan - Jun 1988 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence Jul - Dec 1988 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence 1987 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence Jan - Jun 1990 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence Jul - Dec 1990 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence 1991 and undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence with Tom Kohn, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
  - Correspondence with Perry Brass' mother, 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan - Mar 1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, photographs, poems, notes, and invoices, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence Jan - Jun 1987 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence Jul - Aug 1987 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence Sep 1987 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence Oct - Dec 1987 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Series III. Works
  - Varied-Subject Pad, including drafts of letters, lists, synopsis of "The Chinese Monkey Feast," versions of "At Death's Door," "PCP," a poem inspired by Tom Finley, and other writings (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "All Men" stage notes, program, and notes (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - "All Men" script for publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "All Men" material: Flyers, biographical note, press release, programs, flyers, posters, Christin Bjorn photograph, publicity and promotional material, notes, and reviews, and an interview of Stan Leventhal and Perry Brass (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Manuscript of Jimmie, an unpublished novel (Box 1, Folder 13-19)
  - "Night Chills" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Night Chills" typescript (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - "Gay Success" manuscript and printed version in Advocate Men (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "The Platinum Ring" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "The Platinum Ring" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Taste" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "The Voice Within the Idol" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "At Death's Door" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "On Being Bullied" manuscript and printed version in Torso (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Notes from a Gay Playwright: manuscript and typescript (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "A Blow Job is for Real" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Smoky George Talks" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Drafts of letters (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Varied-Subject Pad, including articles for Stan Leventhal, letters, "Southern Sissy Boy," "Men and Manners" and other writings (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Varied-Subject Pad, including "The Golden Pavilion" manuscript (later called "Spies in the Golden Pavilion"), drafts of letters, and a list ("New in the 60's") (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "The Death of My Friend Tom" manuscript; "Summer on Christopher Street" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "A Regular June" typescript (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Spies in the Golden Pavilion" typescript (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cover (only) of "Survival Kit - A complete Guidance Manual for Gay Men Everywhere" edited by Perry Brass and Lou Thomas (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Sex Stick" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Draft of a letter to the New York Transit Authority, and list of stories (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Dark Mouth" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Lists of venues, poems, bus instructions, and a "Statement of Purpose" (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "The Cold" manuscript, with printed version in Advocate Men (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Disco" manuscript and typescript (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
  - "Bargello" and "Souffle" (two interlinked, one-act plays), manuscript and typescript (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
  - "Unmasking Straight Men" printed version in Torso (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "Meaningless Relationships" printed version in Torso (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - "Threesomes" printed version in "Torso" (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - "Disco" Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "Social Climbing" Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "Gay Anxiety" and "Men Keep House" manuscripts; draft of a letter to Greg Baysans of "The James White Review" and others; preparation notes (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "Straight Men" manuscript (later "Unmasking Straight Men") (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous pieces: draft of a letter to the editor; aphorisms, riddles, and short written pieces on cards; printed version of "The Cincinnati Connection Ballet Comes Alive!"; "Five Gay Plays"; mosaic promotional page for "Urban Fables and Verses"; "Osiris, the Dog Star"; and "The Enticing Lane" by Christopher Hewitt (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Wings Theatre Company broadside and poster for "All Men" (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Typescript of "Unforgettable is Paris" (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Schoolpapers from NYU, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4-12)
  - Copies of "Come Out!" (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - Typescript of "This Is All Of Us" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Untitled early stories, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Early draft of Jimmie (Box 2, Folder 32-37)
  - Professional papers, course description, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Mirage and publicity material (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Sex Charge (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "Sleep" woodcut, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Mirage third draft typescript (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
  - Red-bound spiral drawing tablets, some with homoerotic drawings, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 58-60)
  - Final Disconnect typescript (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Prescription for Love by "Nancy Gwendolyn Bell" typescript (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Homosexual Politics" typescript (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Drafts of short stories, correspondence, miscellany, c.1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Salonica" an original screenplay typescript (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Draft manuscripts, typescripts, poems, and miscellaneous writings (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
  - Poems (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Pet Palmistry" (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Short stories (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Homosexual Politics" draft typescript (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Artwork (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Here, There, and Yonder," a trilogy of one act plays (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Mirage (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sex Charge (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Daddy and the Eskimos" (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Bar None" (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "Bargello" and "Souffle" (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Sex Charge" typescript (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Another Temporary Assignment" draft typescript (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "Night Chills" (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "The Chinese Monkey Feast" (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "The Secret Gate" (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Munchenergarten" (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - "The Most Beautiful Man in the World" (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - "Men Living With Each Other" (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Mirage holograph (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "The Rat Man" holograph (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - "Secret Gate" holograph (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Works" second draft (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  - "Mirage" second draft (Box 5, Folder 11-15)
  - Published pieces in "The Connection" (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
  - "Works" paperback (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Notebooks of draft prose fictions, including "Book Talks - Maugham," "Movers and Shakers," "Mother's Boys," "Take it Slow," "The Freighter Story," "Night Chills," and "The Most Beautiful Man in the World" (Box 5, Folder 26-30)
  - Notebooks of drafts of "The Seventeenth Summer" (Box 5, Folder 31-35)
  - Notebooks of "Set" poem, "The Boathouse," "The Self-Expression Factor," "Bargello," "Poetry Education," and "The Body Queens" (Box 5, Folder 36-39)
  - "The Wounded Angel" (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Series IV. Miscellany, including photographs
  - Photographs of Brass, friends and lovers (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Germany, by Tom Kohn (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, pornography magazines (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellany, including theatre programs, broadside, poem, letter from the Netherlands, photographs, and woodcut (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellany, including photographs, negatives (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Miscellany, including passport, slides, negatives, and photographs (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Esquire" July 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Vogue" December 1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Theatre and musical programs (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Anion Enzyme Educational Conference Center Workbook, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Publicity for Brass publications and readings, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - 2004 Publicity (Box 5, Folder 42)
ADDITIONAL INFORMATION
Key to Perry Brass' original descriptive notes of the material:
Box 1:
"Envelope 7.A" = folders 1-2
"Envelope 5.A" = folders 5-6
"On this pad:" = folder 7
"Envelope 2.A" = folders 11-12
"Manuscript of Jimmie = folders 13-19
"On this pad:" = folder 34
"On this pad:" = folder 35
"Envelope 3.A" = folders 36-41
"On this pad:" = folder 43-44
"Envelope 4.A" = folders 45-46
"In this folder--5.A" = folders 47-48
Box 2 (primarily):
"Perry Brass List of Archive Box 2"
1 = folders 1-3
2 = folders 4-12
3 = folders 13-15
4 = folder 16
5 = folders 17-22
6 = Box 4, folders 1-7
7 = folder 23
8 = folders 24-25
9 = folders 26-27
10 = folder 28
11 = folders 29-31
12 = folders 32-37
15 = folder 38
Box 3 (primarily):
"Perry Brass List of Archive, Box Four"
Item 1 = Box 2, folders 58-60
Item 2 = folder 6
Box 5 (primarily)
"Perry Brass List of Archive, Box Five"
Batch 3 = folders 36-39
Batch 5 = folders 26-30